<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='repotool.1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>repotool</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>May 06 2015</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='productname'>repotool</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>repotool</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Development Tools</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>repotool</refname>
<refpurpose>query or manipulate a CVS, Subversion, git, bzr, hg, or
darcs repository in a uniform way</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>repotool</command>
      <arg><replaceable>action</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice='opt'><replaceable>URL-or-dir</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>repotool is a script wrapper around repository operations that
differ by version-control system.  It is little use by itself,
existing mainly to generate and simplify a conversion makefile usable
with
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>reposurgeon</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>

<para>Not all actions are supported on all systems.  You will get an
error message and a return value of 1 when attempting an unsupported
action.</para>

<para>The "initialize" option takes a project name (and, optionally,
following source and target VCCS types) and generates a
Makefile that will sequence various steps of a repository
conversion. It also generates stub lift and options files. This is
meant to be run in an empty work directory, and it is an error to do
'initialize' where any of these files already exist.  Afterwards, you
will need to set some variables in the Makefile; read its header
comment.</para>

<para>The 'export' action, run from within a repository directory,
dumps a copy of a CVS, Subversion, git, bzr, hg, or darcs repository
to a flat history file readable by reposurgeon. The format is usually
a git-fast-import stream, except that Subversion repositories export
as Subversion dump files; the point is to be a lossless
erepresentation, or as close to one as possible.</para>

<para>The 'tags' option, run from within a repository directory,
returns a list of the repository's release tags.</para>

<para>The 'branches' option, run from within a repository directory ,
returns a list of the repository's branch names.</para>

<para>The 'checkout' option checks out a working copy of the
repository. It must be called from within the repository. It takes one
required argument - the checkout directory location. It may take a
following optional argument which is a tag or revision specification;
if this argument is not given, the tip (most recent) mainline revision
is assumed.</para>

<para>The 'compare' action takes two repository directories and a
revision spec (typically a tag name). If the revision spec is omitted,
the tip of the main line of both repositories will be used.  The
selected revisions are cpmpared with diff -q -r, with noise due to
SCCS/RCS/CVS keyword expansion ignored.  You can follow the command
verb with one or more -x options followed by basenames of paths to
exclude from comparison. You can get a context-diff report on file
differences with the -u option.</para>

<para>The 'compare-tags' action takes two repository directories,
extracts a list of tags from the first, then compares the repository
contents at each tag in the list, generating a compare report for
each.  You can follow the command verb with one or more -x options
followed by basenames of paths to exclude from comparison. You can get
a context-diff report on file differences with the -u option.</para>

<para>The 'compare-branches' action takes two repository directories,
extracts a list of branches common to both, then compares the repository
contents at each branch in the list, generating a compare report for
each.  You can follow the command verb with one or more -x options
followed by basenames of paths to exclude from comparison. You can get
a context-diff report on file differences with the -u option.</para>

<para>The 'compare-all' action takes two repository directories, and
runs all 3 above compare actions on them. Even if the same name is a
tag in one repository and a branch in the other, it will compare them
against each other. Not distinguishing them is useful as CVS tags that
are not applied to every file in the repository may get converted to
branches.  The options are the same as 'compare-tags'.</para>

<para>The 'mirror' action makes or updates a local mirror of a
Subversion or CVS repo. It requires a single argument,
either a Subversion URL or a CVS URL, or the name
of a local mirror directory created by a previous run. The first form
creates a local mirror of the repository in a directory named after
the last segment of the URL, with the suffix
<quote>-mirror</quote> (the local mirror name can be overridden by an
optional) second argument. The second form updates the local mirror,
doing an incremental fetch; just give the mirror directory
name.</para>

<para>Subversion URLs are as specified in the public
documentation for those systems.  CVS URLs must specify a host and
repository path, followed by a '#', followed by a module name.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='requirements'><title>REQUIREMENTS</title>

<para>
The export action is a wrapper around either native export facilities or the
following engines:
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>cvs-fast-export</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
(for CVS),
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>svnadmin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
(for SVN),
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>hg-fast-export.py</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
(for hg).
You must have the appropriate engine in your $PATH
for whatever kind of repository you are streaming.
</para>
  
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>

<para><citerefentry><refentrytitle>reposurgeon</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>

<para>Eric S. Raymond <email>esr@thyrsus.com</email>. This tool is
distributed with reposurgeon; see the project page at <ulink
url='http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon'>http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon</ulink>.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
