<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='repotool.1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>repotool</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>May 06 2015</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='productname'>repotool</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>repotool</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Development Tools</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>repotool</refname>
<refpurpose>query a CVS, Subversion, git, bzr, hg, or
darcs repository in a uniform way</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>repotool</command>
      <arg><replaceable>action</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice='opt'><replaceable>URL-or-dir</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>repotool is a script wrapper around repository query operations
that differ by version-control system.  It is little use by itself,
existing mainly to simplify the generic conversion makefile shipped with
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>reposurgeon</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>

<para>Not all actions are supported on all systems.  You will get an
error message and a return value of 1 when attempting an unsupported
action.</para>

<para>The 'export' action, run from within a repository directory
(within a module directory for CVS), dumps a copy of a CVS,
Subversion, git, bzr, hg, or darcs repository to a flat
history file readable by reposurgeon.</para>

<para>The 'tags' option, run from within a repository directory
(within a module directory for CVS), returns a list of the
repository's release tags.</para>

<para>The 'checkout' option checks out a working copy of the
repository. It takes one required argument - the checkout directory
location. It may take afollowing optional argument which is a tag
or revision specification; if this argument is not given, the tip
(most recent) mainline revision is assumed.</para>

<para>The 'mirror' action makes or updates a local mirror of a
Subversion or CVS repo. It requires a single argument,
either a Subversion URL or a CVS URL, or the name
of a local mirror directory created by a previous run. The first form
creates a local mirror of the repository in a directory named after
the last segment of the URL, with the suffix
<quote>-mirror</quote>. The second form updates the local mirror,
doing an incremental fetch; just give the mirror directory
name.</para>

<para>Subversion URLs are as specified in the public
documentation for those systems.  CVS URLs must specify a host and
repository path, followed by a '#', followed by a module name.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='requirements'><title>REQUIREMENTS</title>

<para>
The export action is a wrapper around either native export facilities or the
following engines:
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>cvs-fast-export</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
(for CVS),
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>svnadmin</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
(for SVN),
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>hg-fast-export.py</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
(for hg).
You must have the appropriate engine in your $PATH
for whatever kind of repository you are streaming.
</para>
  
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>

<para><citerefentry><refentrytitle>reposurgeon</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>

<para>Eric S. Raymond <email>esr@thyrsus.com</email>. This tool is
distributed with reposurgeon; see the project page at <ulink
url='http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon'>http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon</ulink>.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
