<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC 
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='reposurgeon.1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>reposurgeon</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>Aug 24 1994</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='productname'>reposurgeon</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>reposurgeon</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Development Tools</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>reposurgeon</refname>
<refpurpose>surgical operations on repositories</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>rs</command>
  <arg choice='opt' rep='repeat'><replaceable>command</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>The purpose of <application>reposurgeon</application> is to
enable risky operations that version-control systems don't want to let
you do, such as (a) editing past comments and metadata, (b) excising
commits, (c) coalescing commits, and (d) removing files and subtrees
from repo history. The original motivation for
<application>reposurgeon</application> was to clean up artifacts
created by repository conversions.</para>

<para>To keep <application>reposurgeon</application> simple and
flexible, it does not do its own repository reading and writing.
Instead, it relies on being able to parse and emit the repo-command
streams created by git-fast-export and read by git-fast-import.  This
means that it can be used on any version-control system that that has
both fast-export and fast-import utilities.  This set includes git
itself, hg, and bzr.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='options'><title>OPERATION</title>
<para>The program can be run in one of two modes, either as an interactive
command interpreter or to execute commands given as arguments on the
<application>reposurgeon</application> command line. The only difference
between these modes is that the interactive one begins by turning on the
'verbose' option.</para>

<para>Here are the available commands:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>help</term>
<listitem><para>Get help on the interpreter commands. Optionally follow with
whitespace and a command name; with no argument, lists all commands. '?'
also invokes this.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>version</term>
<listitem><para>Report the version of <application>reposurgeon</application>
and the list of version-control systems it directly supports.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>verbose</term>
<listitem><para>'verbose 1' enables progress and statistics messages,
'verbose 0' disables them. 
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>shell</term>
<listitem><para>Execute the shell command given in the remainder of the line.
'!' also invokes this.  
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>read</term>
<listitem><para>With a directory-name argument, this command attempts
to read in the contents of a repository in any supported
version-control system under that directory; read with no
arguments does this in the current directory. If the argument is the
name of a plain file, it will be read in as a fast-import stream. With
an argument of <quote>-</quote>, this command reads a fast-import
stream from standard input (this will be useful in filters constructed
with command-line arguments).</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='limitations'><title>LIMITATIONS AND GUARANTEES</title>

<para>Guarantee: <application>reposurgeon</application> never modifies
the contents of a repository it reads or deletes any repository. The
results of surgery are always expressed in a new repository </para>

<para>Guarantee: Any line in a fast-import stream that is not a part
of a command <application>reposurgeon</application> parses and
understands will be passed through unaltered.  At present the set of
potential passthroughs is known to include the
<command>progress</command>, the <command>options</command>, and
<command>checkpoint</command> commands as well as comments led by
#.</para>

<para>Guarantee: All <application>reposurgeon</application> operations either
preserve all repository state they are not explicitly told to modify
or warn you when they cannot do so.</para>

<para>Limitation: Because <application>reposurgeon</application>
relies on other programs to generate and imterpret the fast-import command
stream, it is subject to bugs in those prograns.</para>

<para>Limitation: Under version-control systems other than git,
fast-import format may not capture the entire repository
state. Presently the only known limitations are:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Under bzr, dumps do not capture information about (a) multiple-author 
commits, (b) bzr custom commit properties (e.g. branch-nick and bugs 
fixed by this change), or (c) empty directories.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Limitation: Subversion/RCS/CVS aren't directly supported because exporting
from them requires fixups of usernames in the committer information to
full email addresses.  Trying to handle that entirely inside this tool
would be excessively messy, so we don't. Instead we let the user
transform repo-command streams and cope with the export/import
separately.</para>

<para>Guarantee: As version-control systems add support for the
fast-import format, their repositories will become editable by
<application>reposurgeon</application>. See the <ulink
url="https://git.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/InterfacesFrontendsAndTools">Git
Wiki tools page</ulink> for a large collection of such tools.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>

<para>Eric S. Raymond <email>esr@snark.thyrsus.com</email>; project
page at <ulink
url='http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon'>http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon</ulink>).</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

