<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC 
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='reposurgeon.1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>reposurgeon</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>Aug 24 1994</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='productname'>reposurgeon</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>reposurgeon</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Development Tools</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>reposurgeon</refname>
<refpurpose>surgical operations on repositories</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>reposurgeon</command>
  <arg choice='opt' rep='repeat'><replaceable>command</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>The purpose of <application>reposurgeon</application> is to
enable risky operations that version-control systems don't want to let
you do, such as (a) editing past comments and metadata, (b) excising
commits, (c) coalescing commits, (d) removing files and subtrees from
repo history, and (e) cutting a repo in two by cutting a parent-child
like, preserving the branch structure of both child repos. The
original motivation for <application>reposurgeon</application> was to
clean up artifacts created by repository conversions.</para>

<para>To keep <application>reposurgeon</application> simple and
flexible, it does not do its own repository reading and writing.
Instead, it relies on being able to parse and emit the repo-command
streams created by git-fast-export and read by git-fast-import.  This
means that it can be used on any version-control system that that has
both fast-export and fast-import utilities.  This set includes git
itself, hg, and bzr. It also implicitly defines a common language of
primitive operations for <application>reposurgeon</application> to
speak.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='options'><title>OPERATION</title>
<para>The program can be run in one of two modes, either as an interactive
command interpreter or to execute commands given as arguments on the
<application>reposurgeon</application> invocation line. The only difference
between these modes is that the interactive one begins by turning on the
'verbose 1' option.</para>

<para>A git-fast-import stream consists of a sequence of commands
which must be executed in the specified sequence to build the repo;
to avoiid confusion with <application>reposurgeon</application> commands
we will refer to the stream commands here as <emphasis>events</emphasis>.
These events are implicitly numbered from 1 upwards.  Most commands
require specifying a selection of event sequence numbers so
<application>reposurgeon</application> will know which events to
modify or delete.</para>

<para>Commands to <application>reposurgeon</application> consist of a
command keyword, sometimes followed by a selection set, sometimes
followed by whitespace-separated arguments. It is often possible to
omit the selection-set argument and have it default to something
reasonable. When the command descriptions refer to a 'second' 
argument, it may actually be first after the keyword with the
selection set omitted.</para>

<para>Here are some motivating examples.  The commands will be
explained in more detail after the description of selection
syntax.</para>

<programlisting>
edit :15               ;; edit the object associated with mark :15

edit                   ;; edit all editable objects

list 29..71            ;; list summary index of events 20..71

list /regression/      ;; list all commits with comments containing 
                       ;; the string "regression"

delete =t &amp; 1..:97     ;; delete tags from event 1 to mark 15

list @rel2.0..@head    ;; List commits frm the "rel2.0" tag to the "head" tag 
</programlisting>

<para>The selection-set specification syntax is an expression-oriented 
minilanguage.  The most basic term in this language is a 
<firstterm>location</firstterm>. The following sorts of primitive locations
are supported:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><firstterm>event numbers</firstterm></term>
<listitem><para>A plain numeric literal is interpreted as a 1-origin
event-sequence number.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><firstterm>marks</firstterm></term>
<listitem><para>A numeric literal preceded by a colon is interpreted
as a mark; see the format documentation for explanation of the 
semantics of marks.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><firstterm>symbolic names</firstterm></term>
<listitem>
<para>The basename of a branch refers to its tip commit.  The name of a tag
is equivalent to its mark, and through that to a commit. Names are
led with @ to distinguish them from command keywords.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>These may be grouped into sets in the following ways:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><firstterm>ranges</firstterm></term>
<listitem><para>A range is two locations separated by "..", and is
the set of events begining at the left-hand location and ending at the
right-hand location (inclusive).</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><firstterm>lists</firstterm></term>
<listitem><para>Comma-separated lists of locations and ranges are 
accepted, with the obvious meaning.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>There are some other ways to construct event sets:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><firstterm>visibility sets</firstterm></term>
<listitem>
<para>A visibility set is an expression specifying a set of event
types. It will consist of a leading equal sign, followed by type
letters. These are the type letters:</para>

<informaltable pgwide='0' frame='all'>
  <tgroup cols='3' align='center'>
    <colspec colname='c1'/>
    <colspec colname='c2'/>
    <colspec colname='c3'/>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>B</entry>
        <entry align='center'>blobs</entry>
	<entry><para>Most default selection sets exclude blobs; they
	have to be manipulated through the commits they are attached
	to.</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>C</entry>
        <entry align='center'>commits</entry>
	<entry><para>&nbsp;</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>T</entry>
        <entry align='center'>tags</entry>
	<entry><para>&nbsp;</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>R</entry>
        <entry align='center'>resets</entry>
	<entry><para>&nbsp;</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>P</entry>
        <entry align='center'>Passthrough</entry>
	<entry><para>All event types types simply passed through,
	including comments, <command>progress</command> commands, 
        and <command>checkpoint</command> commands.</para></entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><firstterm>text search</firstterm></term>
<listitem><para>A text search expression is a Python regular expression 
surrounded by forward slashes (to embed a forward slash in it, use a
Python string escape such as \x2f).</para>

<para>A text search matches against the comment fields of commits and
annotated tags; it also matches against the text of passthrough
objects.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Set expressions may be combined with the operators | and &amp;;
these are, respectively, set union and intersection. The | has lower
precendence than intersection, but you may use curly brackets '{' and
'}' to group expressions in case there is ambiguity..</para>

<para>Here are the available and planned surgical commands:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>read</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>With a directory-name argument, this command attempts
to read in the contents of a repository in any supported
version-control system under that directory; read with no
arguments does this in the current directory. If the argument is the
name of a plain file, it will be read in as a fast-import stream. With
an argument of <quote>-</quote>, this command reads a fast-import
stream from standard input (this will be useful in filters constructed
with command-line arguments).</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>write</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Dump a fast-import stream representing the edited repostory to
standard output (if argument is empty or '-') or, with optional second
argument, to a file.  Fails if the argument exists and is a directory
or anything other than a plain file.</para>

<para>Note: a <command>write</command> with a small selection set is 
a useful way to examine small groups of commits.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>rebuild</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>
Rebuild a repository from the state held by
<application>reposurgeon</application>.  The argument specifies the
target directory in which to do the rebuild; if the repository read
was from a repo directory (and not a git-import stream), it defaults
to that directory.  If the target directory is nonempty its contents
are backed up to a save directory.  Files and directories on the
repository's restore list are copied back from the backup directory.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>list</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>This is the main command for identifying the objects
you want to modify.  It lists commits in the selection set by event
sequence number with summary information. The first column is raw
event numbers, the second a timestamp, and the third the leading text
of the comment.  If there is a second argument, or the first is not
recognized as a selection set, it will be taken as the name
of the file to report to; no argument, or one of '-'; writes to
standard output.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>delete</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Delete a selection set of commits (and their associated blobs,
if any).  The default selection set for this command is empty.</para>

<para>Deleting a commit that has children does not back out the
changes made by that commit, as they will still be present in the
blobs attached to the children.  All it does is lose the metadata
information about when and by who those changes were actually made;
after the delete those changes will be attributed to the deletee's
children.  It is expected that this command will be useful mainly
for removing commits mechanically generated  by repository converters
such as <command>cvs2svn</command>.</para>

<para>Recall that each commit has a list of file operations, each a M
(modify), D (delete), R (rename), C (copy), or 'deleteall' (delete all
files). Only M operations have associated blobs.  When a commit is deleted,
each file operation in the commit (and its associated blob reference)
normally gets pushed forward onto the beginning of each child's
operation list.

The following cases may occur:</para>

<informaltable pgwide='0' frame='all'>
  <tgroup cols='4' align='center'>
    <colspec colname='c1'/>
    <colspec colname='c2'/>
    <colspec colname='c3'/>
    <colspec colname='c4'/>
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>Parent op</entry>
        <entry align='center'>Child op</entry>
        <entry align='center'>Copy forward?</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>Note</para></entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry align='center' morerows='1'>M</entry>
        <entry align='center'>M, D, deleteall</entry>
        <entry align='center'>no</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>Child state of the file supersedes the parent
	state</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>C, R, none</entry>
        <entry align='center'>yes</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>Note that if there are multiple
	children this can result in the blob having multiple
	references to it.</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center' morerows='1'>D</entry>
        <entry align='center'>M, deleteall, none</entry>
        <entry align='center'>no</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para></para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>R, C</entry>
        <entry align='center'>no</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>This combination should be impossible; the
	program will throw an error if it occurs.</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center' morerows='2'>R</entry>
        <entry align='center'>M, C, none</entry>
        <entry align='center'>yes</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>&nbsp;</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>D, deleteall</entry>
        <entry align='center'>no</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>&nbsp;</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>R</entry>
        <entry align='center'>modified</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>The child rename is modified. If the
	renames are X &rarr; Y and Y &rarr; Z, the resulting rename
	will be X &rarr; Z</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center' morerows='2'>C</entry>
        <entry align='center'>M, R, C, none</entry>
        <entry align='center'>yes</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>&nbsp;</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>D</entry>
        <entry align='center'>modified</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>A copy of X to Y followed by a delete of X is
	composed into a rename of X to Y.</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>deleteall</entry>
        <entry align='center'>no</entry>
	<entry><para>Both copies perish in the deleteall.</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center' morerows='1'>deleteall</entry>
        <entry align='center'>M, none</entry>
        <entry align='center'>no</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>M is a file creation.</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='center'>D, C, R, deleteall</entry>
        <entry align='center'>no</entry>
	<entry align='left'><para>This should never happen</para></entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</informaltable>

<para>Deleting a commit will leave any tag pointing to it dangling;
these will be garbage-collected. Children of the deleted commit 
get it removed from their parent set and its parents added,</para>

<para>No <command>blob</command> event can be deleted with this
command; <command>blob</command> events are tied to associated
<command>commit</command> or <command>tag</command> events and are
discarded only when those are.</para>

<para>Deleting a <command>tag</command>, <command>reset</command> or
<command>passthrough</command> event has no side effects.</para>

<para>NOT YET IMPLEMENTED.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>cut</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Attempt to partition a repo by cutting the parent-child link
between two specified commits (they must be adjacent). This operation
may fail if the commit graph remains connected through another path;
the tool will detect this. If the repo was named 'foo', the cut segments
will be named 'foo-early' and 'foo-late'.</para>
<para>NOT YET IMPLEMENTED.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>expunge</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Expunge a file from the repo history. Does not take a selection
set.</para>
<!-- document handling of tags, branches, renames, deletes, copies. --> 
<para>NOT YET IMPLEMENTED.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>coalesce</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Scan the selection set for runs of commits with identical
comments close to each other in time (this is a common form of scar
tissues in repository up-conversions from older file-oriented
version-control systems).  Merge these cliques by deleting all but the
last commit, in order.</para>

<para>The optional second argument, if present, is a maximum time
separation in seconds; the default is 90 seconds.</para>

<para>The default selection set for this command is =C, all
commits. Occasionally you may want to restrict it, for example to
avoid coalescing unrelated "*** empty log message ***" commits from
CVS lifts.</para>
<para>NOT YET IMPLEMENTED.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>mailbox_out</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Emit a mailbox file of messages in RFC822 format representing
the contents of repository metadata. Takes a selection set; members of
the set other than commits, annotated tags, and passthroughs are
ignored (that is, presently, blobs and resets).  If there is a second
argument, or the first is not recognized as a selection set, it will
be taken as the name of the file to report to; no argument, or one of
'-'; writes to standard output.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>mailbox_in</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Accept a mailbox file of messages in RFC822 format representing the
contents of the metadata in selected commits and annotated tags. Takes
no selection set.  If there is an argument it will be taken as the
name of a mailbox file to read from; no argument, or one of '-'; reads
from standard output.</para>

<para>Event updates are atomic; if reposurgeon throws an error while in this
command events updated before the error will keep their changed state,
but no event will be partially modified. Event numbers are validated
before any individual event is updated.</para>

<para>Users should be aware that modifying an Event-Number field will change
which event the update from that message is applied to.  This is
unlikely to have good results.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>edit</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Report the selection set of events to a tempfile as mailbox_out does,
call an editor on it, and update from the result as mailbox_in does.
If you do not specify an editor name as second argument, it will be
taken from the $EDITOR variable in your environment.</para>

<para>Normally this command ignores blobs because mailbox_out does.
However, if you specify a selection set consisting of a single
blob, your editor will be called directly on the blob file.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>These are backed up by the following housekeeping commands, none of 
which take a selection set:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>help</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>Get help on the interpreter commands. Optionally follow with
whitespace and a command name; with no argument, lists all commands. '?'
also invokes this.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>shell</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>Execute the shell command given in the remainder of the line.
'!' also invokes this.  
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>prefer</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Report or set (with argument) the preferred type of repository. This
will have two effects.  First, if there are multiple repositories in a
directory you do a read on, reposurgeon will read the preferred one
(otherwise it will complain that it can't choose among them).
Secondly, if you do a write to a directory, it will build a repo of
the preferred type.</para>

<para>If no preferred type has been explicitly selected, reading in a
repository (but not a fast-import stream) will implicitly set it
to the type of that repository.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>stats</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>
Report size statistics and import/export method information after reading
a repo or stream.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>choose</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Choose a named repo on which to operate.  The name of a repo is
normally the basename of the directory or file it was loaded from, but
repos loaded from standard input are "unnamed".
<application>reposurgeon</application> will add a disambiguating
suffix if there have been multiple reads from the same source.</para>

<para>With no argument, lists the names of the currently stored
repositories and their load times.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>rename</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Rename the currently chosen repo; requires an argument.  Won't
do it if there is already one by the new name.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>restore</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>Add (presumably untracked) files or directories to the repo's 
list of paths to be restored from the backup directory after a 
<command>rebuild</command>. Each argument, if any, is interpreted as a
pathname.  The current restore list is displayed afterwards.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>unrestore</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>Remove (presumably untracked) files or directories to
the repo's list of paths to be restored from the backup directory
after a <command>rebuild</command>. Each argument, if any, is
interpreted as a pathname.  The current restore list is displayed
afterwards.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>view</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>
View a repo through the default GUI browser for its version control
system.  Note that this does not show the edited state held by
<application>reposurgeon</application> in core; it is mainly useful
for doing a quick eyeball check ofter a rebuild command.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>A few commands have been implemented primarily for debugging and
regression-testing purposes, but may be useful in unusual
circumstances.</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>index</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem>
<para>Display four columns of info on objects in the selection set:
their number, their type, the associate mark (or '-' if no mark) and a
summary field varying by type.  For a branch or tag it's the
reference; for a commit it's the commit branch; for a blob it's the
repository path of the file in the blob.</para>

<para>The default selection set for this command is =CTRU, all objects
except blobs.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>resolve</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>Does nothing but resolve a selection-set expression
and echo the resulting event-number set to standard
output. Implemented mainly for recression testing, but may be useful
for exploring the selection-set language.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>names</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>List the names of all knowmn branches and tags.
Tells you what things are legal after @.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>version</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>Report the version of <application>reposurgeon</application>
and the list of version-control systems it directly supports.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>verbose</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>'verbose 1' enables progress and messages,
'verbose 0' disables them. Higher levels of verbosity are available
but intended for developers only.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>echo</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>'echo 1' causes each 
<application>reposurgeon</application> command to be echoed to standard
output just before its output.  This can be useful in constructing regression
tests that are easily checked by eyeball.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><cmdsynopsis><command>script</command></cmdsynopsis></term>
<listitem><para>Takes a filename argument. Reads each line from the file 
and executes it as a command.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='limitations'><title>LIMITATIONS AND GUARANTEES</title>

<para>Guarantee: <application>reposurgeon</application> never modifies
the contents of a repository it reads or deletes any repository. The
results of surgery are always expressed in a new repository </para>

<para>Guarantee: Any line in a fast-import stream that is not a part
of a command <application>reposurgeon</application> parses and
understands will be passed through unaltered.  At present the set of
potential passthroughs is known to include the
<command>progress</command>, the <command>options</command>, and
<command>checkpoint</command> commands as well as comments led by
#.</para>

<para>Guarantee: All <application>reposurgeon</application> operations either
preserve all repository state they are not explicitly told to modify
or warn you when they cannot do so.</para>

<para>Limitation: Because <application>reposurgeon</application>
relies on other programs to generate and interpret the fast-import command
stream, it is subject to bugs in those prograns.</para>

<para>Limitation: Under version-control systems other than git,
fast-import format may not capture the entire repository
state. Presently the only known limitations are:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Under bzr, dumps do not capture information about (a) multiple-author 
commits, (b) bzr custom commit properties (e.g. branch-nick and bugs 
fixed by this change), or (c) empty directories.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Limitation: Subversion/RCS/CVS aren't directly supported because
exporting from them requires fixups of usernames in the committer
information to full email addresses.  Trying to handle that entirely
inside this tool would be excessively messy, so we don't. Instead we
let the user transform repo-command streams and cope with the
export/import separately.</para>

<para>Guarantee: As version-control systems add support for the
fast-import format, their repositories will become editable by
<application>reposurgeon</application>. See the <ulink
url="https://git.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/InterfacesFrontendsAndTools">Git
Wiki tools page</ulink> for a large collection of such tools.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='recovery'><title>CRASH RECOVERY</title>

<para>This section will become relevant only if 
<application>reposurgeon</application> or something underneath it in the
software and hardware stack crashes while in the middle of writing out 
a repository, in particular if the target directory of the rebuild is
your current directory.</para>

<para>The tool has two conflicting objectives: on the one hand, we
never want to risk clobbering a pre-existing repo.  On the other hand,
we want to be able to run this tool in a directory with a repo and
modify it in place.</para>

<para>We resolve this directory with a game of three-directory monte.</para>

<procedure>
<step><para>First, we build the repo in a freshly-created staging
directory.  if your target directory is named
<filename>/path/to/foo</filename>, the staging directory will be a
peer named <filename>/path/to/foo-stageNNNN</filename>, where NNNN is
a cookie derived from <application>reposurgeon</application>'s process
ID.</para></step>

<step>
<para>We then make an empty backup directory.  This directory will
be named <filename>/path/to/foo.~N~</filename>, where N is incremented
so as not to conflict with any existing backup drectories.  
<application>reposurgeon</application> never, under any circumstances.
ever deletes a backup directory.</para>

<para>So far all,operations are safe; the worst that can happen up to
this point if the process gets interrupted is that the staging and
backup directories get left behind.</para>
</step>

<step><para>The critical region begins. We first move everything in the
target directory to the backup directory.</para></step>

<step><para>Then we move everything in the staging directory to the
target.</para></step>

<step><para>We finish off by restoring untracked files in the target
directory from the backup directory. That ends the critical
region.</para></step>
</procedure>

<para>During the critical region, all signals that can be ignored are
ignored.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>

<para>Eric S. Raymond <email>esr@snark.thyrsus.com</email>; project
page at <ulink
url='http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon'>http://www.catb.org/~esr/reposurgeon</ulink>.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

